DEEPAK K. GUPTA

Havikshorst 99, 1083 TP Amsterdam, Netherlands +31(0) · 682362020 ⋄ GuptaDeepak2806@gmail.com LinkedIn ⋄ Google scholar ⋄ Github

Research experience of 2+ years in deep learning and computer vision, 5+ years in mathematical modeling and optimization, with a diverse technical background spanning across engineering physics, mathematics and machine learning. My research interest lies in bridging physics-based approaches and deep learning methods to design highly-reliable prediction models for real-world problems.

EDUCATION

Delft University of Technology, The Netherlands

Sep 2013 - Aug 2017

Shell-NWO Computational Sciences for Energy Research (CSER) Programme PhD in Computational Science

Indian Institute of Technology (ISM) Dhanbad, India

July 2008 - May 2013

Integrated (5 yr.) M.Sc. Tech. in Applied Geophysics Overall GPA: 8.48/10 (Rank 1; Director's Gold Medal)

EXPERIENCE

Informatics Institute (QUVA Lab), University of Amsterdam

Jan 2019 - Present

Postdoctoral Researcher (Deep learning, computer vision)

Amsterdam, Netherlands

- · I am currently involved in the following research projects:
 - Developing deep learning algorithms for object tracking in long-term videos.
 - Developing efficient neural network architectures based on mathematically justified evolution schemes.
 - Supervising students on projects related to medical imaging, biological cell tracking, reducing model decay
 in long-term object tracking, and developing VQ-VAE based generative models for modification of selective
 patches in images.

Shell Technology Center

Nov 2017 - Jan 2019

Researcher (Applied machine learning, computer vision)

Bangalore, India

- · Usupervised/semi-supervised learning based real-time automated detection of energy events in passive microseismic data.
- · Application of deep learning methods in automating parts of seismic data processing.

Faculty of 3mE, Delft University of Technology Researcher

Sep 2013 - Aug 2017

Delft, The Netherlands

- · Deep learning based models for noise reduction and data recovery (Aug 2016 Aug 2017).
 - Developed a stacked autoencoder framework to learn geophysical models for denoising purposes.
 - Explored the potential of convolutional autoencoders in denoising of geophysical data.
- · Topology optimization (TO) for high-resolution designs (PhD project, Apr 2014 Aug 2017).
 - Developed a combined mesh and penalization adaptivity based TO scheme.
 - Established uniqueness bounds and identified numerical artefacts in multiresolution TO methods.
 - $\,$ Formulated a dp-adaptive scheme for high-resolution structural designs.
- · Optimization of metallization design in solar cells (*PhD project*, Sep 2013 July 2017).
 - Developed a novel 2D finite element model for numerical modeling of the electrical parameters.
 - Optimized metallization designs for freeform geometries and variable conditions.

EarthByte Group, University of Sydney

Visiting Student

Dec 2012 - Jan 2013 Sydney, Australia

· Developed a C++ based plate rotation utility in the *GPlates* software.

Schlumberger Asia Services Ltd.

June 2012 - July 2012

Summer Intern

Research Student

Dehradun, India

- · Machine Learning based automated correlation of well logs and identification of lithological features.
 - Developed a pattern-recognition approach based on sliding window and normalized cross-correlation.
 - Implemented the algorithm using *Ocean API* as a plugin for *Petrel* software.

Indian Institute of Technology (ISM)

Jan 2010 - Mar 2013

Dhanbad, India

· Soft computing for intelligent interpretation of petroleum data and characterization of reservoirs (M.Sc. thesis: Mar 2012 - Mar 2013).

- Implemented a least square fitting based semi-automated tool for prediction of missing log data.
- Developed a global optimization based tool for the prediction of reservoir properties.
- Formulated an ant colony method based approach for automated horizon selection in seismic data.
- · Recursive ant colony optimization (RACO) (May 2011 Apr 2012).
 - Proposed a recursive variant of ACO well suited for continuous optimization problems.
 - Tested applicability of RACO on various geophysical examples.
- · Computational seismicity analysis and earthquake forecasting (Jan 2010 Apr 2011).
 - Developed a stress transfer model for Chamoli-Uttarkashi region using *Coulomb* software.
 - Developed Fractal Analyzer, a MATLAB based GUI for earthquake forecasting based on multifractal analysis.

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Computer Languages C, C++, Python, MATLAB, JAVA, C# Software Libraries Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, deal.II

Operating systems Linux, MacOS, Windows

GRANTS/AWARDS/SCHOLARSHIPS

2018 : Shell Special Recognition Award

2014 : Gene Golub SIAM Summer Fellowship

2013-17 : Shell-NWO Computational Sciences for Energy Research (CSER) Fellowship

2013 : Director's Gold Medal at IIT (ISM) Dhanbad

2013 : SEG-ENI Scholarship
2012 : SEG Foundation Grant
2012 : SPG India Student Grant

2008-13 : SHE-INSPIRE Fellowship from Dept. of Science & Tech., Govt. of India

SUPERVISION TASKS

M.Sc. Students

- · 2019 current: Elias Kassapis (UvA); Estimating semantic segmentation uncertainty using a trained discriminator. (tentative, collaboration with TomTom)
- · 2019 current: Max Bos (UvA); Deep learning based identification of patterns/features in ECGs. (tentative, collaboration with UMC Utrecht)
- · 2019 current: Max Filtenborg (UvA); Tracking under object and action constraints (tentative).

- · 2019 current: Dragos Grama (UvA); Real-time tumour tracking during radiotherapy treatment (tentative, collaboration with VUmc).
- · 2019 current: Bryan Cardenas (UvA); Object-specific generative models for large images with multiple objects (tentative).
- · 2019 current: Joaquim Fererra (UvA); Adaptive neural networks (tentative).
- · 2019 current: Alvise Sembenico (UvA); Reducing model decay in long-term tracking (tentative).
- · 2019 current: Andreas Panteli (UvA); Tracking-assisted segmentation of biological cells (tentative). [NeurIPS'19-w]
- · 2019: Dimitrios Tsimpoukis (UvA); Multilabel learning from noisy labeled fashion image data: a semi-supervised approach.
- · 2016-17: Marco Swiestra (TU Delft); Post-Processing of Topology Optimized Results. [thesis]
- · 2016-17: Joachim K. van Schoubroeck (TU Delft); An investigation of the effect of initial design choices in density-based topology optimization. [thesis]

B.Sc. Students

- · 2019: Nathan de Bruin (UvA); Deep learning for cell tracking. [NeurIPS'19-w]
- · 2019: Daan Lee (UvA); Influence of the choice of loss functions on the performance of autoencoders.
- · 2019: Baart van Latum (UvA); Predicting the time of an earthquake event.

Interns

· 2014: Bas Smits (TU Delft, TNO); Optimal design of a solar cell front electrode (co-supervisor).

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- · Gupta D.K., de Bruin N., Panteli A. and Gavves E., 2019, Tracking-Assisted Segmentation of Biological Cells, NeurIPS 2019; Medical Imaging Meets NeurIPS workshop.
- · Gavves E., Tao R., Gupta D.K. and Smeulders A.W.M., 2019, Model Decay in Long-Term Tracking, arXiv:1908.01603.
- · Garg A., Vos A., Bortych N., Gupta D.K. and Verschuur D.J., 2019, Spatial Aliasing Removal using Deep Learning Super-Resolution, *First Break*, 37 (9), 87-92.
- · Gupta, D.K., Shrivastava, R.K., Phadke, S. and Goudswaard, J., 2019, Intelligent Microseismic Event Detection Using Kirchhoff Migration Style Stacking in Combination with Iterative Clustering based Segmentation, 81st EAGE Conference and Exhibition.
- · Bhowmick D., Gupta D.K., et. al., 2019, Stacked autoencoders based machine learning for noise reduction and signal reconstruction in geophysical data, arXiv, arXiv:1907.03278 (under review in Geophysical Prospecting).
- · Gupta D.K., van der Veen G.J., et al., 2017, Bounds for decoupled design and analysis discretizations in topology optimization, *International Journal for Numerical Methods in Engineering*, 111 (1), 88-100.

Full list of publications can be found here.

REVIEWER

Journals : SMO (Springer), IJNME (Wiley), Geophysics (SEG)

Conferences : ICML'19 ICCV'19, ECMLPKDD'19, EAGE'16, EAGE'15, EAGE'14.

CERTIFICATIONS

Machine Learning Nanodegree

April 2018 - Dec 2018

Udacity program on machine learning comprising 6 projects and 1 capstone project

Deep Learning Specialization

Sep 2017 - March 2018

A 5-course-series specialization by deeplearning ai hosted on Coursera

- \cdot Neural Networks and Deep Learning \cdot Structuring Machine Learning Projects
- Improving Deep Neural Networks: Hyperparameter tuning, Regularization and Optimization
- Convolutional Neural Networks Sequence Models

Other MOOCs

Discrete Optimization, Finite Element Method for Physics

Relevant courses

- · Scientific computing · Structural Optimization: Algorithms and Applications
- · Simulation, Optimization, and Identification in Solid Mechanics
- · Introduction to Programming on the GPU · Object Oriented Programming
- · Numerical and Statistical Methods · Methods of Applied Mathematics I & II
- Introduction to Descriptive Statistics Geophysical Signal Processing
- Geophysical Inversion Signal Analysis Theory Discrete Optimization

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

Extracurricular activities

- · Member of DSV Concordia cricket team and played in KNCB cricket tournaments (2015-17).
- · President of EAGE Student Chapter of IIT (ISM) for the term 2012-13.
- · Volunteered as a teacher for more than two years for Kartavya, an NGO run by IIT (ISM) students aimed at providing free education to under-privileged children.
- · Represented India as a team in the finals of the 2009 Global Entrepreneurs' Program conducted by Stanford Entrepreneurs' Society of Stanford University.

Languages

· English (professional proficiency)

- · Hindi (native)
- · Bengali (intermediate)

Hobbies

- · cricket, football and swimming
- · sketching and computer gaming